Finding Aid for the James Marshall Frank Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
James Marshall Frank Papers
2009
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0153
.42 linear feet
Biographical Note
A member of the Fugitive literary group and a brother-in-law of Sidney Mttron Hirsch, James Marshall Frank was a successful manufacturer with an interest in literature and education. Born in Marshall County, Tennessee in 1866, James Marshall Frank spent most of his life in Nashville. An 1885 graduate of George Peabody College, he taught for several years. Financial responsibilities caused him to change careers, and he accepted employment with Frank and Company, a local shirt manufacturer, where he worked for the next 50 years. He married Rose Hirsch, the sister of Sidney Hirsch on November 5, 1902, and they had a daughter Helen, who is the donor of this collection. Many of the meetings of the Fugitive poets were held at his home on Whitland Avenue in Nashville. He died in Nashville on November 21, 1944.
Scope and Content Note
These papers consist primarily of correspondence and manuscript material that Fugitive poet James Marshall Frank collected. Also included here are items that came from him and other Fugitive poets and which were donated to Special Collections by his daughter Helen Frank. Donald Davidson, Laura Riding Gottshcalk, Sidney Hirsch, Merrill Moore, Allen Tate, and Robert Penn Warren are among the Fugitive poets whose work is represented, and there are also letters to and from various members of the Frank and Hirsch families.
Frank’s collected issues of Skyline and The Archive feature poems by Frank and other Fugitive poets. The collection is .417 linear feet.
- Correspondence
  - Outgoing Correspondence from Helen Frank
    - June 4, 1928 - June, 1964 (Folder 1)
      - June 4, 1928 to family
      - August 7, 1934 to Mrs. James Frank
      - June, 1964 to Louise Davis
  - Outgoing Correspondence from Sidney Hirsch
    - August 29, 1913 - November 22, 1918 (Folder 2)
      - August 29, 1913 to Helen
      - May 2, 1914 to Jess
      - September 14, 1914 to Jim Frank
      - January 7, 1917 to Rose
      - February 2, 1918; February 7, 1918 to My dear family
      - March 14, 1918; April 18, 1918; November 22, 1918 to Jim
    - February 8, 1925 - July 14, 1925 (Folder 3)
      - February 8, 1925; February 15, 1925 to All
      - February 17, 1925 to Elsie
      - February 26, 1925 to All
      - March 6, 1925 to Jim
      - March 22, 1925; July 14, 1925 to All
    - November 17, 1925 - October 20, 1936 (Folder 4)
      - November 17, 1925 to Jim
      - May 14, 1926
      - April 30, 1926 to All
      - June 1, 1926 to All
      - June 1926
      - October 20, 1936 to Rose, Jim, Helen
    - Incomplete dates (Folder 5)
    - Incomplete dates (Folder 6)
  - Outgoing Correspondence from Merrill Moore
    - August 26, 1929 - December 13, 1938 (Folder 7)
      - August 26, 1929 to Miss Rose
      - November 10, 1929 to Hirsch - Franks
      - June 8, 1930 to Miss Rose
      - November 7, 1932 to Helen
      - December 31, 1933 to Miss Rose
      - April 20, 1937 to Miss Rose
      - May 11, 1938 to Mrs. Rose
      - June 30, 1938 to Rose
      - December 13, 1938 to Rose
    - February 3, 1939 - September 1, 1950 (Folder 8)
      - February 3, 1939 to Helen
      - October 20, 1939 to Mr. Jim and Miss Rose
      - March 1, 1940 to Miss Rose
      - March 1, 1941 to Mr. Jim
      - December, 1943 to Miss Rose
      - Thanksgiving 1944 to Rose, Jim, Elsie, Helen
      - January 7, 1948 to Helen
      - September 1, 1950 to Rose
    - September 11, 1957 - July/August 1948 (Folder 9)
  - Incoming Correspondence to Helen Frank
    - Brittingham, Dr. and Mrs. Thomas - n.d. (Folder 10)
    - Brittingham, Mrs. Thomas (Dotsy), January 23, 1981
    - Bynner, Witter, November 5, 1921
    - Cheney, Frances Neel (Fannie), August 10, 1956
    - Dahl – Wolfe, Louise, May 18, 1972
    - Davis, Louise, June 10, 1964
    - Frank, Lois (Mrs. Morris), December 30, 1977
    - Gottschalk, Laura Riding, December 3, 1924; April 30, 1925; June 3, 1925; August 5, 1925; August 31, 1925 (Folder 11)
    - Gottschalk, Laura and Louis - n.d., April 30, 19?
    - Nasse, Paquerette, March 6, 1966 (Folder 12)
    - Stewart, John L., June 19, 1964
  - Incoming Correspondence to James Marshall Frank
    - Earnest, D.L., April 24, 19? (Folder 13)
    - Hume, Alfred, April 24, 1922
    - Stuart, Jesse, October 24, 1934
    - Tate, Allen, October 14, 1927
    - Witcover, H.W., December 12, 1924; February 21, 1928
  - Incoming Correspondence to Rose Hirsch Frank (Mrs. James)
    - Frank, Jim, June 30, 1934 (Folder 14)
    - Nauen, October 16, 1936
    - Starr, Milton, July 8, 1928
    - Tate, Allen, November 30, 1944
    - Untermeyer, Jean Starr, April 12, 1930
    - Yum, Helen, October 20, 1936; August 1, 1940
    - Zener, Karl, June 3, 1928
  - Incoming Correspondence to Sidney Hirsch
    - Hal, December 31, 1921 (Folder 15)
    - Ralph, September 29, 1916
- Poems - Manuscripts - James Marshall Frank
  - Mirrors (2 handwritten copies) (Folder 16)
  - Two Sonnets
  - 11 The Book of How
  - Garden Waters
  - Croesus in Autumn (Folder 17)
  - Pro Sua Vita
  - San Francisco Night Windows
  - Lines with No Title
  - Cora is Dead (4 copies) (Folder 18)
  - I proffered you a mountain chain of love...
  - The Wind
  - To R.H.F. (4 copies)
  - To R—
  - The Terrible (Folder 19)
  - Stranger Guest
  - Silhouette
  - Pegasus at the County Fair (2 copies)
  - On My Birthday, (April 16, 1929; 2 copies) (Folder 20)
  - Muses (Singing) (a dramatic poem; 4 pages)
  - Husband Betrayed (Folder 21)
  - The Helmeted Minerva
  - Genealogy
  - For Example (3 copies)
  - Esperance (Folder 22)
  - Complexity (Folder 23)
  - Coils
  - Buddy II
  - August
  - But when he is put up for sale... (2 copies) (Folder 24)
  - From the point the circle drawn... ( 2 copies)
  - A soldier once went valiantly to fight...
  - Plucked from a pristinate garden…
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Folder 25)
- Poems - manuscripts - other authors
  - Davidson, Donald (Folder 26)
    - A little eye against a brain
    - Crabbed Youth and Age
  - Gottschalk, Laura Riding
    - Address to Shelley
  - Moore, Merrill (Folder 27)
    - Certain Room
    - Naked and Drenched
    - Oh, Mariner, oh Master Mariner
  - Notes in Defense of Ecstasy:
    - Physiology
    - Relativity
    - Conflict
    - Thought, Distraught
    - Meeting in a Garden
    - Epithalamion of a Peach
    - Swine, Wine
    - L’Etat C’Est Moi
    - Misanthropy
    - Vain Protestations
    - Tones and Comparisons
    - Disappointment of a Thrall
    - In Bed, Not Dead
    - Primer of Science
    - Fait Accompli
  - Pilcher, Cobb
    - Purpose
  - Tate, Allen (Folder 28)
    - Shadow and Shade
    - The Mediterranean (2 copies)
  - Warren, Robert Penn
    - Old Man One Hour Before Dawn
- Plays - manuscripts - James Marshall Frank
  - Potophor’s Wife (12 Pencil Manuscript Papers) (Folder 29)
  - Savonarola (pencil manuscripts in notebook) (Folder 30)
  - Sudaveh - Queen of Persia (drama in 5 Acts) (Folder 31)
  - Scraps of handwritten manuscripts (Folder 32)
- Articles and clippings
  - Photocopies: (Folder 33)
    “Cora Leventhal Martin: A Tribute from a Girlhood Friend” by Rose Hirsch Frank
    “Member of Associated Retailers Welcomes Visitors to State Fair”
    “The Fugitive” (1923)
    “New York Woman and Massachusetts Man Win $100 Nashville Poetry Contest” (1923 - 1924)
    “New Fugitive is Published”
    “Nashville Poets Will Read Saturday”
    “Nashville Poets Read Originals Before Poetry Society Meeting”
    “The Phoenix Nest” from Saturday Review of Literature (February 16, 1929)
    “The December Issue of The Fugitive is an Unusually Interesting Number,” by George Bond
    “The World of Letters: Ransom Comment on Books and Bookmen” from Review of Books
    “The Outland Piper,” by Donald Davidson, Has Lyrical Passion,” by Hilton R. Greer
    “Integrity, Patience, Discipline” A review of John Crowe Ransom’s Selected Poems From the New York Times, July 8, 1945
    “Ransom at 84: New Book, Old Times” from New York Times, May 17, 1972
    “Grant Brings No Obligation: Robert Penn Warren Nabs $300, 000 Prize” by Carey Winfrey
    “Fugitives’ Regroup to Study, Be Studied on Beginnings, Literary Contributions” by Ralph Morrissey
    “Literary Group Meets at VU to Study Fugitive Poets” by Bruce Williams from The Nashville Banner, May 3, 1956
    “Fugitive Meetings Recorded; Poets Themselves May Pen Versions of Rare Sessions” by Ralph Morrissey from The Tennessean, May 6, 1956
    “Fugitive Sampling” - short poems by nine of the Fugitive poets
    “Literary Leaders to Meet at VU for 3 - Day Parley of Fugitive Poets” from the Nashville Banner, May 1, 1956
    “Assignment, Nashville: Fugitive Thoughts on ‘Fugitive’ by Eddie Jones
    “Fugitive Stumped by Reunion Purpose”
    “Fugitives’ Hark Back 30 Years to Capture Spirit of Fine Poetry” by John Seigenthaler from The Nashville Tennessean, May 3, 1956
    “Our Girl Friday says: Parties, Poetry Mixes for VU Fugitive Group” from The Nashville Tennessean, May 4, 1956
    “Spirit of Fugitives Flare Up Anew” by John Seigenthaler from The Nashville Banner, May 5, 1956
- Publications
  - Skyline, a college literary magazine, published at the Cleveland College of Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio: (Folder 34)
    Volume 1, no. 3 ,January 1929
    Volume 2, no. 1, May 1929
  - The Archive, a monthly publication at Duke University, Durham, North Carolina: (Folder 35)
    Volume XLI, no. 4, January 1929
    Volume XLI, no. 5, February 1929
    Volume XLI, no. 7, April 1929
    Volume XLII, no. 6, May 1930
    Volume XLII, no. 7, April 1930
- Documents
  - 3 Ex Libris James M. Frank bookplates by Sidney Hirsch (Folder 36)
  - 3 Miscellaneous pencil drawings
  - Order and Travel papers for Reconstruction Aide, Sadie Frank, February 2; 3, 1919
  - Wedding Invitation of Rose Lee to James Marshall Frank, November 5, 1902
  - Addressed to John P. Frank’s document of money transfer from Goldie D. and Nathaniel D. Hirsch to James M. Frank, July 1, 1915
  - Document granting patent to Sidney M. Hirsch, June 9, 1917
  - Letter to J.M. Frank about patent, June 13, 1917
- Memorabilia
  - Brown leather covering of The Fugitive dedicated to “President S. Mttron-Hirsch, 1922 - 1925”; inscribed by Donald Davidson and Walter Clyde Curry (Folder 37)